Okay בוקר טוב Boker tov today's דף daf is מ"ד mem-daled and
we pick up מ"ג עמוד ב mem-gimel amud bet and we pick
up with the two dots פעם אחת לא נכנסו לנמל. paam achat
lo nichnasu l'namel. So we're still dealing with being on a boat
and you land and once you land are you if you went
from חוץ לתחום chutz l'tchum because you are now 2000 אמות amot
outside of where the boat was when שבת Shabbos began then you
could only have four אמות amot and you only have four אמות
amot from where you are. So I'll go back and review some
of the הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh aspects that we discussed about that
yesterday about whether you have enclosed space that you enter into and
whether you have תחומין tchumim above 2000 אמות amot off the ground
above 10 טפחים tefachim off the ground but the גמרא Gemara anyway
looks at the משנה Mishnah assuming that all those are a problem
and the case in the משנה Mishnah could they get off of
the boat? Could they debark?
Didak? No, de-plane.
Disembark, thank you.
Anyway so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said, oh no, no, I was
looking as we were getting close and I saw that we were
within 2000 אמות amot when שבת Shabbos began. So does so you
know they don't they can't necessarily walk home but they can get
off the they can disembark get off the boat. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. What?
He said he can't hold that opinion כמאן דאמר כהרף עין זה
יצא וזה נכנס ואי אפשר לצמצם עליו. k'man d'amar k'heref ayin zeh
yatza v'zeh nichnas v'ee efshar l'tzamtzeim alav.
Alright, so yeah it would have to be, you know it's a
good question about exactly where you were. You'd have to say from
the beginning of בין השמשות. bein hashmashot. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: תנא, tana, so פעם אחת לא נכנסו לנמל
paam achat lo nichnasu l'namel they didn't get into the port until
after שבת. Shabbos. תנא, tana, so now we have a ברייתא braita
to explain exactly what happened. שפופרת הייתה לו לרבן גמליאל. shfoferet hayta
lo l'Rabban Gamliel. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel had a שפופרת shfoferet a
tube I'll discuss well it sounds like a telescope yes שהיה מביט
וצופה בה אלפיים אמה ביבשה. she-haya mabit v'tzofeh bah alpayim ama bayabasha.
He would look through it and be able to determine 2000 אמות
amot on dry land וכנגדו אלפיים בים. uk'negado alpayim bayam. And therefore
he was able to correspond to 2000 אמות amot on the sea
and see when they was into 2000 אמות amot or not. Now
how do you do that with a telescope? So רש"י Rashi says
that this telescope רש"י Rashi says it's not exactly a telescope it's
not for seeing long distances. רש"י Rashi actually says that it actually
shortens the distance that you can see. That apparently it has a
smaller aperture at the end and therefore this is רש"י Rashi I'm
before you jump on me I know the problems with it therefore
it limits how far you can see. So you so basically you
either collapse it or extend it to open or close the opening
at the end and then when it's to a point where you
can only see 2000 אמות amot and you'd figure that out by
measuring then you know that wherever you can see by looking through
this is 2000 אמות amot distance. So you measure on the land
and then you're able to use it even on the sea and
say if something if I can see something it means it's within
2000 אמות. amot. The of course problem with this is that even
if you have a small opening it doesn't limit the length of
the distance that you can see it limits your field of vision
but it doesn't limit the length of the vision you can see.
So it's very hard to understand from רש"י Rashi how this worked.
I looked at the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz and he quoted the גאונים Geonim
and others that say that it was not a something for a
that it was basically what are those things called that they have
gradations and a sextant or something? No. What is that no a
sextant is a shamash in the shul. What?
What does he say there?
What does he have in that picture? He's got a picture of
the you're not in the English? Anyway so so he says that
it's it's an actual type of a thing that based on the
angle and that you use you use it for with using some
type of math which I don't understand anyway he says that that
you can use to estimate distances and that that's actually what they
use to even nowadays in surveying. Are those I mean don't people
see them sometimes looking at tripods? Tripods and the angles and some
type of a thing.
He doesn't have it in that picture book?
I don't think it's not going to have it in here.
So this
would
be מדידת medidat
well if he was doing it on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos.
One
suggests that maybe it's like the the focal length is such that
you that you know you can see to a certain point it's
like it's focused for a point of 2000 אמות. amot. Oh so
that it is within focus. That's an interesting thing that maybe maybe
that's a way of reading רש"י. Rashi. What Dov is suggesting is
not that you can't see further but that it's focused on a
point that's 2000 אמות amot away. So that if that thing is
within focus then that then you know that it's 2000 אמות. amot.
Maybe that's a way of reading רש"י. Rashi. Okay so it was
some type of a device. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on
it
says
was a laser
a laser pointer right so now the גמרא Gemara goes on it
says okay הרוצה לידע כמה עומקו של גיא harotzeh leida kama omko
shel gei
if you want to know the depth of a of a
valley מביא שפופרת mavei shfoferet so you bring this same device ומביט
בה וידע כמה עומקו של גיא umabit bah v'yeida kama omko shel
gei again
assuming you have it you have it you
know adjusted calibrated thank you for 2000 אמות amot based on measurements
you've done on flat ground you know on flat ground and you've
actually measured so then. Now you use that same angle, that same
calibration, and you can figure out what the length is at the
depth of the valley or the other way רש"י Rashi would say,
or the other way is, is that probably you do it the
reverse. First you get it so that it's measuring a particular point
in the depth of the valley, then you use that same calibration
and you see how far you get on flat land and you
can see how deep the valley is. So however this device works,
you can also use it for things that otherwise you couldn't measure,
like ocean or the depth of a valley, based on measurements you've
done on dry land. Now, הרוצה לידע כמה גובהו של דקל, Ha-rotze
leida kama govho shel dekel, let's say you want to see how
high a palm tree is. So presumably you could do the same,
but it has even a better example. You know they have these
things for measuring the room, these like laser pointers that bounce off
the walls or whatever, apparently they're like very inaccurate. So yeah, that's
what I read stuff on that. Anyway,
but here it has a better way of figuring out the height
of a palm tree. How is this? מודד קומתו וצלו, Moded komato
v'tzilo, you measure your height and then the length of your shadow,
וצל קומתו, v'tzel komato, and then you measure the length of the
shadow of the palm tree on the same day, you know standing
in the same position, and therefore, and therefore it, you know, it's
proportional, right? וידע כמה גובהו של דקל V'yeida kama govho shel dekel
and you'll know how high the palm tree is. Everybody understand that
logic, right? It's perfect sense. Yeah, I mean if this is you
and this is the palm tree, all right? So your, if your
shadow is let's say twice as long as you are, so then
you measure the shadow of the palm tree and you divide by
two. If your shadow is one and a half then you divide
by one and a half or if your shadow is half your
length you whatever multiply by two. That actually makes a lot of
sense. Okay. הרוצה שלא תשרה חיה רעה בצל קבר. Ha-rotze she-lo tishre
chaya ra'ah b'tzel kever. Now this is, I don't know where this
is coming from because this is not exactly about measurements, but okay.
But it's about shadows. הרוצה שלא תשרה חיה רעה בצל קבר. Ha-rotze
she-lo tishre chaya ra'ah b'tzel kever. You don't want animals to be,
particularly evil animals meaning like poisonous animals or biting animals or whatever,
to be resting in the shade of your of a tombstone. Apparently,
you know, you want to go visit the grave and you don't
want scorpions and whatever things to sort of be around there. So
what do you do? נועץ קנה בארבע שעות ביום. No'etz kaneh b'arba
sha'ot ba-yom. You stick a, you know, a stick into the ground
when it's 10:00 AM, four hours into the day, ויראה להיכן צלו
נוטה, v'yeira'eh l'heichan tzilo noteh, and you see where the shadow goes,
because apparently that's when it starts getting warm at 10:00, and that's
where all the animals will come to hide where it's shady at
that time. So you see where the shadow is cast at
10:00, ומשפיע ועולה משפיע ויורד, umashpia v'oleh mashpia v'yored, and therefore what
you do is you actually build a mound so that it doesn't
actually cast a shadow. Right? If this thing, if at 4:00 this
thing is casting its shadow, you know, to the east and its
shade hits over here at the end of the shadow, I make
a mound like this so there's no area that's shaded, you know,
in that space at 10:00. רש"י Rashi says oh well once they're
not finding shade at 10:00 they're not going to bother to go
there during the rest of the day either. I don't know. Find
another spot. Find another spot and they'll camp out there. Right. Exactly.
So okay. נחמיה בריה דרב חנילאי. Nechemya brei d'Rav Chanilai. Now that's
the end of the, that was the end of the ברייתא. braita.
Now נחמיה Nechemya the son of רב חנילאי Rav Chanilai משכתיה שמעתא.
mashchatya shmata. He got very involved in his learning. Literally it means
his his study,
his סוגיא sugya drew, right, drew him away. He was so head
in the clouds that he was walking, he didn't know where he
was walking. ונפק חוץ לתחום V'nafak chutz la-tchum and he walked outside
of the תחום. tchum. And now he can't get back into the
city. So אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב נחמן. Amar lei Rav Chisda
l'Rav Nachman. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב נחמן, נחמיה
Rav Nachman Nechemiah תלמידך, נחמיה Nechemya your student, שרי בצער shari b'tza'ar
is dwelling in discomfort. He's out there and he, you know, he's
stuck. אמר לו, Amar lo, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman, said to
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, עשו לו מחיצה של בני אדם. Asu lo
mechitza shel b'nei adam. Here's how we're going to solve. Make a
wall of people, ויכנס v'yikanes and let him enter into the wall
of people. Which means basically, so we, and this is important ties
into what we said yesterday, according to the position of רב, Rav,
who rules like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel in the משנה, Mishna, even
if you are, if you went outside the תחום, tchum, if within
your four אמות amot you can go to an enclosed space, you
can walk the entire enclosed space. So how are they going to
go into an enclosed space? I mean he's out there in the
middle of the thing. Get a hundred, get ten people together, surround
him, make a big circle around him, and that's an enclosed space.
And then what, and they go חוץ לתחום chutz la-tchum to get
to him?
Yeah, that's a good question. Presumably רש"י Rashi says all of them
will assume have made some type of an עירוב eiruv or something
which is a little bit... Or didn't go too far.
What? You could imagine they started closer.
They started closer, the houses are more, right, the houses are more
at the edge of the, you know, he didn't go too far.
Right. Exactly. So okay. So now, okay, so that's the, so that's
the answer. Right. You'd have to say that they either made an
עירוב eiruv or that they started closer to that spot. So that's
the solution. So by the way that's important because it basically is
that we rule like
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
They're constantly moving.
So right, so the גמרא, Gemara, what, so let's take a look
because that ties into the next line of גמרא. Gemara. So גמרא
Gemara says like this: יתיב רב נחמן בר יצחק אחוריה דרבא. Yativ
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak achorei deRava. So רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak
was sitting behind רבא, Rava, ויתיב רבא קמיה דרב נחמן, veyativ Rava
kamei deRav Nachman, and רבא Rava was in front of רב נחמן
Rav Nachman when this discussion between רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רב
חסדא Rav Chisda were going on. אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק
לרבא, Amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak leRava, so רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, who was the third back there, said
to רבא, Rava, מאי קא מבעיא ליה לרב חסדא? Mai ka mibaya
lei leRav Chisda? What's, you know, what's bothering רב חסדא? Rav Chisda?
Meaning, why did רב חסדא Rav Chisda need this answer from רב
נחמן? Rav Nachman Why wasn't this like, I don't know, self-evident?
רב חסדא Rav Chisda told him that רב נחמן Rav Nachman? נחמיה
is in trouble and רב נחמן Rav Nachman gave him this solution.
So he wanted to know like, you know, what's bothering רב חסדא?
Rav Chisda? Who knows? Maybe רב חסדא Rav Chisda wasn't, you know,
didn't think of the solution, but somehow he understood that there was
some potential problem with this solution. What's the potential problem that רב
חסדא Rav Chisda had? אילימא בדמלו גברי עסקינן. Ilima bidmalo gavrei askinan.
If you say that there are enough people to get him, you
know, get him back within the
two thousand אמות. amot. That's the case. וכמיבעיא ליה הלכה כרבן גמליאל
או אין הלכה כרבן גמליאל? Vekamibaya lei halacha keRabban Gamliel o ein
halacha keRabban Gamliel? And his question is, do we rule like רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel or not? Do we say that you can, if
your four אמות amot gets you within an enclosed space, you can
go the entire enclosed space? And if that enclosed space gets you
back within your two thousand אמות, amot, then once you get back
in, right, you're safe. Do we say that? או דילמא
בדלא מלו גברי עסקינן, O dilma bidlo malo gavrei askinan, that no,
no, no, certainly רב חסדא Rav Chisda assumed you can rule like
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. If you can get into that enclosed space,
you're fine. But the problem is he maybe couldn't get into that
enclosed space. Why not? Because there weren't enough people. וקא מיבעיא ליה
הלכה כרבי אליעזר או אין הלכה כרבי אליעזר? Veka mibaya lei halacha
keRabbi Eliezer o ein halacha keRabbi Eliezer? Do we rule like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or not? Now, what's this רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer?
So this ties into a question some people were asking yesterday. What
happens if, you know, here's your two thousand אמות? amot? We say
once you step out you're limited to four אמות. amot. But says
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says two follow-up things.
Number one, he says your four אמות amot are not four אמות
amot in every direction. They're two אמות amot in each direction. Okay?
You're in the center of the four אמות. amot. But that's a
חומרא. chumra. But the קולא kula is, if after you step out
you're within two אמות amot of the city, your four אמות amot
overlap the two thousand אמות, amot, then you're still within the two
thousand אמות. amot. Okay? So you actually get not two thousand אמות,
amot, but you get two thousand and two, according to רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. חכמים Chachamim disagree. They say once you're one step out,
even if your four אמות amot overlap, it doesn't matter, you've gone
over the line. Okay. Now, so the question is, maybe the case
is it's that we don't have enough people to bring him—no, I
should have brought the pens. Anyway, but here's the case, right? Here
is your two thousand אמות. amot. It ends here. You can make
a corridor of people like this from the end of the two
thousand אמות amot to where he's standing. But even that corridor, okay,
only doesn't get you to the guy, it gets you within two
אמות amot of the guy. So the question is, certainly we can
use those people, certainly if you could get into the enclosed space
you're okay. But the point is that you can't get to the
guy, you can only get to, or, I'm sorry, you know, you
can only get to right within two אמות amot of the guy.
Now he doesn't have enough people. Now the question is, and this
is תוספות's Tosafot's question, who needs enough people? You just make a
circle around the guy and you just keep on moving, right? So
you make successive, like, you know, spaces. So תוספות Tosafot asks that
question and we're going to see at the end of this discussion
that the people who are making the wall around him have to
be somewhat oblivious. Why, we'll see later. Okay? But it's a good
question, who needs it to be one big extension, why don't you
do multiple, just move with a circle? But that's the גמרא's Gemara's
question. Why was there an issue here? Of course this is obvious.
Maybe the question is, do we rule like רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel?
Or maybe the question is, what happens if you're only—if you can't
get all the way to the guy? So let's take a look.
So it says like this... let me just find twenty...
okay...
right... so it says like
this... רש"י Rashi says by the way, it's not that, right, it's
because it's not that you would extend this and it would be
within two אמות amot of the guy, but it would be the
opposite, you would sort of get this around the guy and that
even with—same basic point, but even though you've got this wall and
it's around this guy, he would only get to within two אמות
amot of the city. Okay? So let's take a look. So it
says like this... וכמיבעיא ליה הלכה כרבי אליעזר או אין הלכה כרבי
אליעזר? Vekamibaya lei halacha keRabbi Eliezer o ein halacha keRabbi Eliezer? פשיטא
בדלא מלו גברי עסקינן. Pshita bidlo malo gavrei askinan. It must be
the issue is that you don't have enough guys. Why must that
be the issue? בדלא מלו גברי עסקינן. Bidlo malo gavrei askinan. דאי
בדמלו
גברי עסקינן, De'i bidmalo gavrei askinan,
because if we assume you do have enough guys, מאי קמיבעיא ליה,
mai kamibaya lei,
what would be the question whether you rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel or not? הא אמר רבא הלכה כרבן גמליאל בדיר וסהר וספינה.
Ha amar Rava halacha keRabban Gamliel bedir vesahar vesafina. רבא Rava says
we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel in a דיר, dir, a
סהר, sahar, and a ספינה, safina, and therefore, and why... And why
is this obvious here that we're going according to רב Rav, *Rav*?
One minute.
All of
them agreed about this ספינה *sefinah*.
Yeah, but this wasn't the ספינה *sefinah* case. This was a דיר
וסהר *dir ve-sahar*. You didn't start שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* within that space.
Not clear why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming necessarily that this
would be going according to רב Rav *Rav*, but okay. הלכה halakha,
כרבי גמליאל בדיר וסהר וספינה *Halacha ke-Rabbi Gamliel bedir ve-sahar ve-sefinah*. אלא
ela, ודאי בלא מלאו גברי עסקינן *Ela vadai belo milu gavrei askinan*.
לרבי אליעזר קמיבעיא ליה *Le-Rabbi Eliezer kamibaia lei*. It must be that
there were not enough people. So yes, they could get him into
their band of people, but the people themselves couldn't necessarily reach all
the way back to the 2,000 אמות amos. *amot*. They could only
get within
the 2,000... only within two אמות amos *amot* of that space outside
the 2,000. And the question is do we go like רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*? דיקא נמי דקאמר ליה יכנס *Deika nami dekamar
lei yikanes*. Actually, that's you could be in the you can see
that from the words he used, because he said, let's, you know,
surround him with people and let him enter in. מאי יכנס *Mai
yikanes*? What does it mean let him enter in? לאו בלא מחיצה
mechitza *Lav belo mechitza*? It must mean enter, meaning enter from that
band of people into the 2,000 אמות Amot *amot*. So presumably he
leaves the enclosure of people and he then he enters into the
תחום techum *techum*. So there's actually a gap because he used the
phrase יכנס *yikanes*. Of course, יכנס *yikanes* could mean just, you know,
that band of people takes him into the 2,000 אמות Amot, *amot*.
But somehow it's understood, again, if you've got him here, right, and
you've got this band, this band of people gets him within the
two, and then let him leave that circle of people and enter
into the 2,000 אמות Amot. *amot* so that there's that gap because
he
gets those two אמות Amot *amot* like
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. Because those two אמות Amot *amot*
are like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* and that is...
wouldn't he just never need to go to the bathroom? Once he
has to do that, then it would be that gap.
Yeah, he could have done that too. Okay, so now let's see
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. Again, it's not clear to me
why it assumes that we go necessarily like רב *Rav*. But anyway,
okay. So it says like this: בעי רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא
*Ba'ei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak le-Rava*. רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak* asked רבא Rava *Rava* in terms of this whole solution:
is the solution of surrounding with people necessarily work? So it says
like this: נפל דופנה nafal dofna, לא יעמיד בה אדם בהמה behema.
וכלים *Nafal dofna lo ya'amid bah adam behema ve-kelim*. Now we're going
to get another problem which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* didn't even think
was an issue, which is can you use people—two questions: can you
use people as a wall, and can you make a wall on
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* or יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*? Are you
allowed to make a wall on שבת Shabbos? *Shabbat* or יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov* out of people? Out of people, maybe that's
like a problem of building. So let's take a look. Here's a
ברייתא Braisa, *beraita*. If a wall of your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* fell
down, נפל דופנה לא יעמיד בה אדם בהמה behema וכלים *nafal dofna
lo ya'amid bah adam behema ve-kelim*, you cannot, you know, rebuild that
wall of that... that wall of your סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* on סוכות
Sukkos, *Sukkot* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* itself. And not
only obviously can you not rebuild it like with, you know, construction
material, you can't even make a person stand there or get an
animal to stand there or pile up vessels to serve as the
wall, even a very temporary wall. ולא יזקוף את המיטה *Velo yizkof
et hamita*.
Even if your wall was originally an animal, which you're allowed to
do for סוכה sukkah. *sukkah*?
Yes, but you can't do it on יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom
Tov*. You can't build a wall on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay,
ולא יזקוף את המיטה לפרוס עליה סדין *velo yizkof et hamita lifros
aleha sadin*. And don't sort of upturn the bed and use the
bed frame and spread a blanket over the bed to make that
into a wall. לפי שאין עושים אהל עראי ohel arai. בראשונה ביום
טוב *Lefi she-ein osim ohel arai barishona be-Yom Tov*. That's like making
a tent, a like building, even though it's not the roof of
the tent, it's the wall of the tent. You cannot make a
wall on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, even if it's only temporary, even
clearly by the way you're doing it it's only temporary. ואין צריך
לומר בשבת ve'ein tzarich lomar beShabbat, *Ve-ein tzarich lomar be-Shabbat*. And you
certainly couldn't do it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. So how can you
do this? Very nice, you've solved the problem, yeah, but by using
people to make a wall, you've made a wall on שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbat*. So how are you allowed to do it? So אמר ליה
amar leh, את אמרת לי מהא *amar lei at amart li meha*,
you want to show me from this that you're not allowed. ואנא
אמינא לך מהא *Ve-ana amina lach meha*. I'll show you from this
following ברייתא Braisa, *beraita* that you are allowed. What does the ברייתא
Baraita, *beraita* say? עושה אדם את חברו דופן *Oseh adam et chavero
dofen*. You are... you can use your friend as a wall for
a סוכה sukkah. *sukkah* כדי שיאכל וישתה ויישן *kedei she-yochal ve-yishte ve-yishan*,
in order that you should eat and drink and sleep in the
סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. You can use a person to serve as a
wall. ויזקוף את המיטה ויפרוס עליה סדין כדי שלא תלקה חמה על
המת *Ve-yizkof et hamita ve-yifros aleha sadin kedei shelo tilke chama al
hamet*, or let's say it's not a סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* case. You
can go ahead and stand up your bed frame and put a
blanket on it and make essentially a shade, a wall to provide
shade, so that a corpse does not sort of rot in the
sun. ועל האוכלין *Ve-al ha-ochlin*, and so it doesn't sort of spoil
food. So you are allowed to make a wall, a temporary wall,
on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat* and יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay, so I
say it is allowed. So fine. So now we have a contradiction
of ברייתות Braisas *beraitot*. So what's the story there? Maybe it's a
מחלוקת תנאים Tannaim. *machloket tannaim*? Maybe there's some other way of reconciling
it? קשיא אהדדי *Kashya ahadadei*. They contradict one another. לא קשיא *Lo
kashya*. It's not difficult. הא ha, רבי אליעזר הא רבנן Rabbanan, *Ha
Rabbi Eliezer ha Rabbanan*. It's a debate of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
and the רבנן *Rabbanan*. Not the רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* we quoted
before about the two אמות Amot. *amot*, but a different רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* and the רבנן *Rabbanan*. דתנן *Detnan*, we learned in the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*: פקק pkak החלון *Pekak hachalon*. You've got a stopper
of a window. רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*: בזמן שקשור ותלוי
*bizman she-kashur ve-talui*, if it is, this window stopper, instead of a
shade, is tied to... is suspended from the ground by a string
and it's tied to the wall, so clearly it's like a part
of the wall, like a door. Like a door, we don't say
closing your door is adding to the wall cause it's all part
of the same contraption, it's all connected. So רבי אליעזר says if
you've got this window stopper that's all connected, it's basically like a
type of
shutter, it's on a string and it's tied to the wall and
it's suspended, so then you haven't added anything. Then it's allowed. If
it's קשור ותלוי, kashur vetalui, פוקקין בו. pokekin bo. ואם לאו, ve'im
lav, but if not, if it's not connected or suspended, אין פוקקין
בו, ein pokekin bo, you can't use it cause it's like you're
adding to the wall. וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say,
בין כך ובין כך פוקקין בו, bein kach uvein kach pokekin bo,
either way you can add to it. So it seems like there's
a debate between, what is this, when it's not tied to the
wall, you are adding to the wall, why is it allowed? Presumably
cause it's only temporary. So presumably the debate of the חכמים Chachamim
and רבי אליעזר is can you do a temporary wall on שבת.
Shabbat So that's the issue of can you make a wall out
of people for your סוכה, sukkah out of a bed frame for
your סוכה, sukka can you make a temporary wall on שבת. Shabbat
So it's a debate of תנאים.
Wait, but didn't we have this before though about שבת? Shabbat I
know, I know, I know, but didn't we also have there before
that everyone agreed שאין עושין אהל עראי ביום טוב? she'ein osin ohel
arai beyom tov?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, so that's
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. But right now we
think that the debate is can you make a temporary wall on
שבת Shabbat, and יום טוב. So that's the debate of the ברייתות
braitas and that's what the issue is around surrounding him with people.
So the גמרא Gemara says like Michael said, one minute. The גמרא
Gemara says ואיתמר עלה, ve'itmar alah, but what we said to explain
this debate, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, הכל מודים שאין עושים אהל עראי
ביום טוב, hakol modim she'ein osim ohel arai beyom tov, everybody agrees
that to really make a temporary wall on יום טוב you cannot
do, ואין צריך לומר בשבת, and certainly that's true on שבת. Shabbat
So what's the debate about the window stopper? לא נחלקו אלא להוסיף,
lo necheleku ela lehosif, there the wall exists and you're only making
a temporary addition, שרבי אליעזר אומר אין מוסיפין ביום טוב ואין צריך
לומר בשבת, sheRabbi Eliezer omer ein mosifin beyom tov ve'ein tzarich lomar
beShabbat, רבי אליעזר doesn't even allow you to make a temporary addition
on יום טוב and certainly not on שבת. Shabbat וחכמים אומרים מוסיפין
בשבת ואין צריך לומר ביום טוב, vechachamim omrim mosifin beShabbat ve'ein tzarich
lomar beyom tov, and חכמים Chachamim say you can make. But that's
a temporary addition. This is not an addition. This is an entire
wall. So how are you allowed to do it? So we are
still stuck. אלא, ela,
so how do you explain the ברייתא, Baraita, how do you explain
the fact that you allowed us to do it? אלא, it says
where were we, אלא לא קשיא
הא
רבי מאיר הא רבי יהודה. ela lo kashya ha Rabbi Meir ha
Rabbi Yehuda. It's about the debate about whether you can or can't
is between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא,
detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita עשה לבהמה דופן לסוכה. asah
lebehema dofen lesukkah. Let's say you wanted to use, not on סוכות,
ערב סוכות, erev Sukkos, you wanted to use an animal as your
wall for a סוכה. sukka, רבי מאיר פוסל ורבי יהודה מכשיר. Rabbi
Meir posel veRabbi Yehuda machshir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can't
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can. Either because רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is afraid the animal will wander off or there's an
intrinsic reason that if it's a live thing, if it's an animal,
halachically somehow for some categorical reason it can't be defined as a
wall. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's not good. Okay, so
what the גמרא Gemara is trying to answer and this is like
a really hard to understand what the הווה אמינא hava amina is,
as רש"י Rashi himself says, is that הא, the reason you can
make the wall out of the animal is because it halachically doesn't
work as a wall and that's why you can make it according
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So you really didn't do anything. Of
course it says you're making the animal so you can eat in
the סוכה. sukka. So what do you mean? But anyway, but that's
what the גמרא Gemara is trying to say. You can do it
because it didn't work. So we're going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So the גמרא Gemara says רבי מאיר דקפסל התם, Rabbi Meir dekapasel
hatam, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there says
it's no good, אלמא לאו מחיצה היא, alman lav mechitzah hi, it's
not meaningful to have your animal stand there, it's not really a
wall, it's just an animal, it doesn't even count as a wall.
So therefore הכא שרי, hacha sharei, he would allow it here. דלאו
מידי קעביד, delav midi ka'avid, you're not doing anything. רבי יהודה דקמכשר
התם, Rabbi Yehuda dekamachshar hatam, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says an animal's
good, אלמא מחיצה היא, alman mechitzah hi, so you're doing something, והכא
אסיר, vehacha asir, here it's forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא,
vetisbra, does that make sense? That when it says you can use
the animal it's going according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? First of
all it says you can use the animal so you can eat
in there. So obviously
it does not seem to work. But anyway, ותסברא, vetisbra, does that
really make
sense? אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי מאיר בבהמה. eimur deshamat leih leRabbi Meir
bebehema. First of all he only said it by a בהמה. When
we said you're allowed to do it it was also אדם וכלים,
adam vekelim, people or vessels. So אדם וכלים מי שמעת ליה, adam
vekelim mi shamat leih, when did you ever hear him say that
you could do, that it was a problem to use people? Now
you might say if it's a problem to use a בהמה it's
a problem to use a person, but how about vessels? פשיטא, pashita,
of course according to him you can just pile up chairs and
tables and whatever. So nobody would say that's not good for a
wall. Number one. And two, and in addition, רבי מאיר אליבא דמאן?
Rabbi Meir aliba deman? First of all you haven't really solved the
problem because who is he going like? אי אליבא דרבי אליעזר, i
aliba deRabbi Eliezer, if you're going according to רבי אליעזר, להוסיף נמי
אסור. lehosif nami assur.
So you can't even add. Meaning even if it is not a
halachic wall but you're still adding to the existing structure. So let
me just check רש"י Rashi a second. לאו קביעות ולאו קביעות אלא
פקק החלון. lav keviyut velav
keviyut ela
pekak hachalon. By right, right. Okay, fine. אלא אליבא דרבי אליעזר Ella
aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer להוסיף תנא יוסיף. lehosif tana yosif. אלא אליבא
דרבנן. Ella aliba d'Rabbanan. So that it would
be according to the רבנן,
and you know, so he must be saying, so what you've said
basically, it's not a halachic wall according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So fine, so it's not a halachic wall according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but
why does it make it allowed? You know, so what are you
going to call it? You're not going to call it something of
significance. You'll call it like a temporary thing. So doing on שבת
Shabbat now? Yeah, doing adding the fourth wall on שבת Shabbat according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, or sorry, adding this wall made out
of an animal for your סוכה sukka. according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So אלא אליבא דרבנן. Ella aliba d'Rabbanan. So fine, you'll say
it's going according to the Rabbis, but one minute, אימא דאמרי רבנן
להוסיף לכתחילה מי אמר? eima d'amri Rabbanan lehosif lechatchila mi amar? So
the גמרא Gemara is assuming here that even though
it's not a
halachic wall, right, as רש״י Rashi says, you know, the פקק pkak
of the חלון chalon is also not a halachic wall. Things aren't
all of a sudden allowed just because they're not halachic, although we're
actually going to say that in a minute, but anyway. So he
says that would be like, so what do you want to say?
You want to say that it's that it's like just like adding
the פקק pkak of the חלון. chalon. It's no worse than adding
the פקק pkak of the חלון chalon since it's not doing anything
of halachic of significance. But fine, but according to the Rabbis,
that's adding the פקק there's an existing structure. Here there's not an
existing structure. This is עושה לכתחילה. ose lechatchila. So let's see so
so we don't understand. Anyway, that whole answer of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir was very bizarre because it's because why would you do something
if it was not doing any halachic purpose? So let's see, so
the גמרא Gemara, says אלא הא והא רבנן. Ella hava hava Rabbanan.
So rather it's both according to the Rabbis that whether you can
or can't add the fourth wall. Really? So whether you can or
can't add a wall. How could it be according to the Rabbis
who say that it would count as a wall? So what's the
issue? Here's the issue. וכלים אכלים לא קשיא. Vekelim akelim lo kashya.
I'm sorry, yeah, אלא הא והא וכלים אכלים לא קשיא. Ella hava
vekelim akelim lo kashya. So what's the issue about whether you can
use the vessels? One says you can, one says you can't. הא
בדופן שלישית הא בדופן רביעית. Ha bedofen shlishit ha bedofen revi'it. It
depends whether it's the third wall or the fourth wall. דיקא נמי
דקתני נפל דופנה שמע מינה. Dayka nami dektani nafal dofna shma mina.
And that can be inferred because it says its wall fell down.
If you go back and look at the ברייתא, braita look back
on you know higher up where we quoted the ברייתא, braita. it
said the following, right? It said going back to the top of
the עמוד, amud, eight lines from the top, the first thing says
נפל דופנה, its wall, לא יעמיד בו אדם בהמה וכלים ולא יזקוף
את המיטה לפרוס עליה סדין. lo ya'amid bo adam behema vekelim velo
yizkof et hamita liphros aleha sadin. So its wall means a wall
that's necessary for it halachically. That's what you're not allowed to do.
And if you look at the next ברייתא braita, where it says
you are allowed to do it, it says עושה אדם את חברו
דופן כדי שיאכל וישתה ויישן ויזקוף את המיטה, ose adam et chavero
dofen kedei sheyochal veyishteh veyishan veyizkof et hamita, right? So it doesn't
say its wall, it says a wall. And it basically says that
the difference here is is whether can you make a wall or
not on שבת Shabbat or not. It depends on whether it is
a halachic wall or not. And this is actually an important issue
which is, there's two definitions of אהל. ohel. One definition or really
the fundamental definition of אהל ohel is a roof, right? That's an
אהל, ohel, a roof. And when we say you cannot make a
temporary אהל ohel לכתחילה lechatchila on שבת, shabbos, we mean you can't
make a roof. So for example, people aren't aware of this, but
like you can't take some chairs and spread a blanket over and
make
like a little tent for kids to play under.
That's making a roof on שבת Shabbos even though it's only completely
temporary. That's אין עושין אהל עראי לכתחילה בשבת. ein osim ohel arai
lechatchila beShabbat. A wall is not exactly an אהל, ohel, but this
גמרא gemara basically says and another גמרא gemara says the same thing,
a wall constitutes an אהל ohel when it is actually doing a
halachic function, when it's halachically serving as a wall to define like
a רשות, reshut, you know, to define a part of a סוכה,
sukka to define a sort of a wall around me so that
I can go in it within the תחום techum. on שבת Shabbos
and so on. That is serving as some type of like a
significant role and therefore that's like making an אהל ohel לכתחילה lechatchila
on שבת Shabbos, when it is a what do you call it,
when it is a halachic wall. So therefore says the גמרא, gemara
can you make another wall on your סוכה sukka. on שבת Shabbos.
or יום טוב? Well, it's the Rabbis that say you can make
an אהל עראי. ohel arai, So making a wall is consider they
say you can מוסיף mosif on an אהל עראי, ohel arai but
you can't make it לכתחילה. lechatchila. So making it לכתחילה lechatchila means
would constitute if I made a halachic wall. So to make the
third wall I can't do. That's like I created something new on
שבת Shabbos. even though it's only temporary. Yeah, but you're not but
you right, why don't you say you're being מוסיף mosif on the
other three on the other two walls? But that's the point. You're
not being מוסיף mosif on the other two walls, you're making a
wall that in itself is defined as a halachic wall. Okay, so
that's what you can't do. When what can you do is if
there are three walls you can make the fourth, because then you're
just being מוסיף mosif on what exists. And even if you're not
being מוסיף, mosif, even if you're just making this wall סתם stam
out in the middle of nowhere, you're for example allowed to like
it says you're allowed to make a wall to protect the מת
met so that it's shaded from the stuff. It's not. adding on
any existing structure. As long as it's not a halakhic wall you're
allowed to do it. So the third wall is no good, that's
making something new, a fourth wall or a separate wall which you
don't need four walls for סוכה sukka or סתם stam a wall
out in the middle of nowhere, which is just there to provide
shade, that's not considered to be creating making an אהל עראי on
שבת, Shabbos. it's not considered to be doing anything. In this case
the people, although it is serving halakhic purpose for him to be
in a תחום. techum? So that's what the גמרא's gemara question is
going to be. So how do we use the people to surround
him to do halakhic purpose you haven't solved the problem you solved
the contradiction of the ברייתות braitas? whether it was allowed or not
but what you haven't solved is the issue about how can they
surround him. Okay. So now it says like this. אלא אדם אדם
קשיא. Ela adom adom kashya. We have a difficulty about people against
people. Okay, so how come one ברייתא braita says you're allowed to
use people and the other says you're not? Now, one minute. One
minute. Right so if you take a look, let's go back and
look at the cases of the ברייתא. braita So the case was
like this again if you take a look at the ברייתא, braita
the first one says going back to the עמוד א amud alef
it says like this. נפל דופנה זו, Nafal dofenah zu, meaning the
third wall of the סוכה, sukka. לא יעמיד בה בהמה וכלים. lo
ya'amid ba bahamah vekeilim. Okay. Then it says ולא יזקוף את המטה
לפרוס עליה סדין לפי שאינו עושה אהל עראי בתחילה ביום טוב. velo
yizkof es hamitah lifros aleha sadin lefi she'eino ose ohel arai betchilah
beyom tov. So the one that said you can't do it, all
of the cases were to make the third wall of the סוכה.
sukka. So that's why that ברייתא braita everything is no good, right,
because you can't make the third wall of the סוכה. sukka. Okay.
Now but the next one says עושה אדם את חבירו דופן כדי
שיאכל וישתה וישן oseh adom es chaveiro dofen kedei sheyochal veyishteh veyishan
ויזקוף את המטה ויפרוס עליה סדין כדי שלא תיפול חמה על המת
על האוכל. veyizkof es hamitah veyifros aleha sadin kedei shelo tipol chama
al hames al ha'ochel. So we have the case about protecting the
מת mes and protecting the food. That's okay, it's not a halakhic
wall. But why does it say that you can use your friend
כדי שיאכל וישתה וישן, kedei sheyochal veyishteh veyishan, that you can sleep,
if you need him to make it a good סוכה so he's
doing a halakhic wall. So we have one of these cases still
says you can use a person to be the halakhic wall in
the סוכה. You see everybody's got that? One ברייתא braita says everything
is no good. That's when it was the third wall. The other
ברייתא braita says everything is good. That's when it wasn't the wall.
But one of the cases of the ברייתא that said it's good
was when your friend is serving as a halakhic wall. Who says?
Maybe he's just blocking the wind for you. No it says כדי
שיאכל וישתה וישן. kedei sheyochal veyishteh veyishan. To me those are the
acts that you're allowed to do that you need a סוכה to
do. Anyway the גמרא gemara says אלא אדם אדם קשיא. ela adom
adom kashya. You solved everything. What's no good is to serve as
the third wall. What is good is to do some non-halakhic wall
function. But why does it say that you can use your friend
to serve as the third wall in one of the ברייתות? braitas.
So the גמרא gemara says אדם אדם נמי לא קשיא. adom adom
nami lo kashya. That's not difficult. כאן לדעת כאן שלא מדעת. kan
ladaas kan shelo madaas. Whether is the person aware that he is
actually serving as the wall or not. If he's not aware, if
he's just standing there, stand there, ah that's perfect, I want you
to stand there the whole night. I want to see what you
look like as you're standing there. And somehow that somehow is not
considered to be creating something, presumably because the whole issue here I
imagine is that human beings are not objects. So the idea that
you can use a person to he's defined as a wall is
a little bit like is a little funny. Have you really made
him a wall? He's really a person, he's not a thing. So
I think that maybe that somehow is informing this issue that if
somehow he acknowledges that he's there to serve as a wall then
it's seen as something somehow like more significant of what you've done.
If he himself is unaware then you can't really say you've defined
him as a wall. Of course the problem is that you're still
playing it both ways. He's enough of a wall that he allows
you to eat in your סוכה. He's not enough of a wall
that it's considered like I made a wall on שבת ויום טוב.
shabbos veyom tov. So I'm allowed to sort of split the vote
and do it both ways. But that's the הלכה, halachic you can
use a person to even be a halakhic wall as long as
he's unaware. The גמרא gemara so that's what the גמרא's gemara about
to say. So that's how we resolve the ברייתות. So one ברייתא
everything is no good. That's when it's serving as a halakhic wall,
the third wall of the סוכה. One ברייתא everything is fine. That's
when it's serving non-halakhic functions, it's providing shade or whatever. Ah it
says you can use a person to be the third wall of
a סוכה. So that tells us that if the person's unaware it's
allowed. So now the גמרא gemara says even where if he's making
a halakhic wall. So now the גמרא gemara says והא רב נחמיה
בריה דרב חנילאי לדעת הוה? vehas Rav Nechemia brei deRav Hanilai ladaas
hava? One minute, that case was that it said was with awareness,
it said go bring people out. So the גמרא Gemara says שלא
מדעת הוה. shelo madaas hava. No, who says they were aware? Why
don't you sort of say hey guys, come, let's go visit I
hear who was it that was stuck out there, I hear חנניה
Chananya is out there, let's go visit him see how he's doing
and you all get around hey let's all I hear he just
got married recently, let's all sing a do a circle dance around
him anyway it says שלא מדעת. shelo madaas. The גמרא Gemara, says
to this by the way is why תוספות Tosafos says you couldn't
have done successive things because that would have made them
aware. So the
גמרא Gemara. says part of the group that made the wall, he
was just coordinating it. Very bizarre issue here about how they think
they can actually arrange it, but הלכתית halachically it's quite significant because
הלכתית halachically this becomes part of an idea that you cannot you
can make a temporary wall on שבת Shabbos. as long as it's
not a הלכה halachic wall. You can't make a temporary אוהל ohel
but you can make a temporary wall. And there are cases of
this like for example one of the early references we have to
the presence of a מחיצה mechitza was there's a מרדכי Mordechai that
says when the women come to hear the דרשה drasha of the
רב, you put up a they're allowed to put up a מחיצה
mechitza. for צניעות tznius because you know modesty keeping the men and
women separate and it's not considered a הלכה halachic wall because it's
just there for modesty purposes. It's not a הלכה halachic wall meaning
that it's defined as a classic עשרה טפחים asara tefachim high in
order to הלכתית halachically define either a wall of an enclosure or
to הלכתית halachically separate two רשויות. reshuyot. This is just for privacy
purposes, you know, modesty purposes. So it's an interesting question, what do
you mean when the women come here to hear the דרשה? drasha?
Where were they before that? So actually in the time of the
ראשונים Rishonim we see in other places that the women דאווען davened
in a separate room from the men, maybe even a separate building,
but the רב doesn't want to give the דרשה drasha twice. So
you have the women all come in, but then they have to
put up a מחיצה. mechitza So it's actually interesting. It's quite I
should say that there's an interesting הלכה halachic implication about this about
the מחיצה mechitza because
there's debates about what the function of a מחיצה mechitza is, you
know, in a שול. shul. So if it's about sort of serving
some practical purpose so that one side can't see the other side
or interact with the other side, then it's not הלכה halachic in
the sense that it's not defined as your classic עשרה טפחים asara
tefachim wall, you know, which is whose purpose is to define an
enclosure or to formally separate two רשויות. reshuyot. But there is an
opinion, רב הענקין Rav Henkin says, you know, quotes his father that
he says no, that actually the מחיצה's mechitza fundamental role is to
הלכתית halachically define them as two separate רשויות reshuyot and therefore in
principle עשרה טפחים asara tefachim could be enough. And there are some
שולן shuls that actually still some OU שולן shuls that are left
that still have מחיצות mechitzas that are only עשרה טפחים asara tefachim
high, which is basically thirty inches, maybe three feet or so on.
So רב משה, Rav Moshe, you know, very strongly disagrees with this.
But according to רב הענקין Rav Henkin brings down that, you know,
according to his grandfather רב יוסף אליהו הענקין Rav Yosef Eliyahu Henkin
that really it's fundamentally there to just designate them as separate places,
not to practically, you know, make it obstruct interaction. So therefore עשרה
טפחים asara tefachim is enough. By the way it's a חומרא chumra
also because he says that if let's say the מחיצה mechitza starts
more than שלושה טפחים shlosha tefachim off the ground but goes very
high, is it good? So if it הלכתית halachically has to be
a wall it has to be within שלושה טפחים shlosha tefachim of
the ground. So in one of his תשובות teshuvos he actually is
criticizing a certain קיבוץ kibbutz he was at that their מחיצה mechitza
started more than three, it was like a screen that started whatever
some type of a fabric that started שלושה טפחים shlosha tefachim off
the ground. Anyway, so according to that approach, you couldn't make it
on שבת Shabbos because then it's actually serving as a הלכה מחיצה
halachic mechitza as defining a הלכה halachic wall. So I was once
at a בר מצוה bar mitzvah where they were at what? The
מחיצה mechitza didn't know it was a wall.
Yeah, right, the מחיצה mechitza.
didn't know. So that only works for people. So I was once
at a בר מצוה bar mitzvah where they had everything set up
outside, it was שבת, Shabbos and then it was like bad weather
so they moved it all indoors and they needed to ad hoc,
it wasn't at a שול shul it was a private home, they
needed to ad hoc set up a מחיצה. mechitza So they were
doing something that was only עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. I said if
it's only עשרה טפחים asara tefachim you can't do it on שבת.
Shabbos You have to make it high!
You have to rule that the function of the מחיצה mechitza is
not a הלכה halacha wall, you have to make it bigger so
you're allowed to do it on שבת. Shabbos Anyway, alright, so now,
but that is the הלכה halachic about the issue about making a
הלכה wall. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara ends this whole discussion
with about this about using a wall out of people. So it
says, הנהו בני גננא, hanhu bnei ganana, people of the of like
a gardeners, דאייתו מיא במחיצה שבני אדם, de'aytu maya bemechitza shebnei adam,
that they used this this מחיצה to bring water
presumably from I don't know there was a well out in the
garden into the house on שבת.
Shabbos, It was outside the תחום?
techum Well, or maybe it was just an issue of רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, right? Once you're using people for a wall you could
also use it to make a space into a רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. So נגדינהו שמואל, nagdinhu Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel gave them lashes. אמר
אם אמרו שלא מדעת יאמרו לדעת. amar im amru shelo mada'at yomru
lada'at. If they allowed it by people, right, that was only if
the people weren't aware. If they're aware it's like making a wall
on שבת. Shabbos הנהו זיקי דהוו שדיין בריסתקא דמחוזא, hanhu ziki dahava
shadin beristika deMechuza, there were various flasks that were that were thrown
in the street of מחוזא. Mechuza. בהדי דאתי רבא מפרקי, bahadi de'asi
Rava miperki, when רבא Rava, was going out of the... out of
the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and of course he was surrounded with
all the students like you know those you know that classic painting
of like Plato and Socrates you know surrounded by the students or
whatever. So that's like the image. So he's going out of the
בית מדרש Beis Medrash and he's surrounded by students and there's a
circle around him. So עיילוה ניהליה Alinhu Ni'alai so they brought—they brought
him into him. Meaning to say they used the fact that he
was surrounded with students so somebody picked as they were traveling picked
up the flasks and walked with the students and was surrounded and
the students were unaware. And you know so that was fine. לשבתא
אחריתא L'shabsachristai the next שבת Shabbos ועילינהו va'alinhu they wanted to use
the same—the same trick. ואסרו להו Ve'asru lehu he said you're not
allowed to דהוו ידעי d'aviyu ke'yadaas and now everybody knows the trick
so now it's forbidden. Okay. לוי עייל ליה תבנא Levi ayil lei
tivna for לוי Levi they used a surrounding of people to bring
in straw. זעירי אספסתא Zeiri asfasta for זעירי Zeiri it was אספסתא
asfasta which was I don't know some other type of fodder. רב
שימי בר חייא מיא Rav Shimi bar Chiya maya and for רב
שימי בר חייא Rav Shimi bar Chiya water and it doesn't of
course explain again the issue of how they did it with people
being unaware. So this whole idea that you can use people if
they're unaware it's hard to imagine how many cases
you have of this.
But you can't know what's in somebody else's mind if they're aware.
I say hey guys let's all—let's all make a wall of people
so we can bring out the—bring this water out from the middle
of the street then they're aware. I mean it's not a question
of having כונה kavana it's not a question of saying הנני מוכן
ומזומן Hineni muchan u'mezuman it's being aware. If you've told them and
they were listening they're aware you know. So but—so
that's the issue about people and I do want to just make
a second and go back to talk about the fact of what
I said that the... so we do פסקן pasken though this whole
issue was—was saying you can make a wall around him on שבת
Shabbos assuming you can out of people or whatever then he certainly
can go into it and go in that whole space. And we
פסקן pasken like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel even בדידית דסוהר b'didiyah de'sohar
that even if somebody's outside the תחום techum if they can get
within their ד' אמות daled amos into—or if they can get surrounded
by a space then they can you know by walls then they
can—then they can travel the whole space. And that as I said
is very relevant because if you land on a—if you're on a
plane and somehow you got stuck with takeoff or landing and you
land on שבת so even if you've gone outside of the תחום
techum you you know if they don't make you go down on
the tarmac which sometimes they do but if you know they've got
what's the tube called? Whatever it is—jetway—if they got that jetway so
then basically you go straight within—straight within a surrounded space and you're
okay. So and the other point I should just mention I mentioned
this yesterday as well but just הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh so I
want to read it is—is about how we rule in terms of
תחומים למעלה מעשרה techumim lemala me'asara because a lot of those cases
you're also basically you know if you're up in the air you're
למעלה מעשרה. lemala me'asara. And then so the only issue that was
raised is when you land and then from the point you land
until it does its you know till it does
its—what's it called—taxiing right
then maybe you've gone already 2,000 אמות. Amot, I get and I
have to look into whether when you actually do land are you
considered on the ground yet because you're still—still clearly למעלה מעשרה lemala
me'asara but you've got a base of more than you know ארבעה
טפחים four tefachim and it is all connected to the ground. So
is that like the גמרא'ס Gemara's you know is that still like
the גמרא'ס Gemara's case of the pole or not? I have to
check that. But anyway but here it says—just to read you the
שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch this is סימן ת"ד siman taf-daled המהלך חוץ
לתחום למעלה מעשרה טפחים כגון שקפץ על גבי עמודים שגבוהים י' ואין
בכל אחד מהם ארבעה על ארבעה טפחים Hamahalech chutz la'techum lemala me'asara
tefachim k'gon she'kafatz al gabei amudim she'gevohim yud v'ein be'chol echad mehem
arba al arba tefachim so you basically jump from one pole to
the next and none of them are four by four טפחים. tefachim.
Then it says הרי זה ספק אם יש תחום למעלה מעשרה אם
לאו harei zeh safek im yesh techum lemala me'asara im lav we
don't know if this is considered תחום Techum, above ten. ומה שיהיה
בדרבנן יהיה ספק להקל U'mah she'yehei bi'derabbanan yehei safek lehakeil so since
it's דרבנן derabbanan it's all going to be לקולא. l'kula. And תחומים
techumim are דרבנן. derabbanan. And the רמ"א Rema basically says that even
if it's—and now the question is that how about the fact that
there's some opinions that when it's not just 2,000 אמות Amot which
is one מיל mil but when it's actually 12 מיל mil that's
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says והואיל ואין בים
ובנהר איסור תחומין דאורייתא לדברי הכל v'hoeil v'ein beyam u'benahar issur techumim
d'oraisa l'divrei hakol he basically even if we say 12 מיל mil
is דאורייתא d'oraisa by תחומים techumim that's only on the ground. In
the air or on the ocean or whatever everybody agrees that תחומים
techumim is not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So it's always going to be a
דרבנן rabbinic question if you're למעלה מעשרה. lemala me'asara. And since it's
a debate we're always going to go לקולא. l'kula. So basically the
effective פסק psak is אין תחום למעלה מעשרה. ein techum lemala me'asara.
So he says ומי שבא בספינה בשבת u'mi she'ba bisafina be'Shabbos if
you come in on a boat on שבת and you're higher than
ten טפחים tefachim off the base you know off of the ocean
floor assuming you're not going in a very shallow והגיע לנמל v'higia
l'namel and you've got into the port like our case in the
משנה Mishnah. אם משנכנס השבת עד שהגיע לנמל לעולם היתה למעלה מעשרה
מקרקע הים או הנהר im mishi'nichnes ha'Shabbos ad she'higia l'namel l'olam hayata
lemala me'asara mi'karkas hayam o' hanahar
if you were always above ten you never got within ten יורד
ואינו נמנה ויש לו אלפיים אמה ממקום שפגע בו למטה מעשרה yoreid
v'aino nimnah v'yesh lo alpaim ama mi'makom she'paga bo lemata me'asara and
as soon as you hit the ground that's where your אלפיים אמה
alpaim ama start okay and therefore you can
disembark. actually landed on שבת *Shabbos*. Okay. And a cruise ship... a
cruise ship also. Exactly. Wherever it is. Check. Yep, exactly. All right.
Let's now start the next משנה
*mishna*. מי שיצא ברשות *Mi she-yatza birshus*.
Now, that was that it was against your will, you had no
choice, but, you know, the non-Jew somehow forced you out there. There
we say you only have ארבע אמות arba amot? *arba amos* from
once you leave. Okay. Or if you're not in one of these
cases about surrounded by walls. But let's say you actually left in,
and you were allowed to go חוץ לתחום *chutz l'techum*. What's the
case? Interestingly, it doesn't say here, it says in ראש השנה *Rosh
Hashanah*, מסכת ראש השנה *maseches Rosh Hashanah*, it says what are the
cases you're allowed to leave. Because there it spoke about leaving the
תחום Techum *techum* in order to go give testimony on the new
month. And then it spoke about other cases like a midwife going
to help a woman give birth, helping somebody that's in danger of
life. When you're going to do a מצווה *mitzvah*, not just, right,
yeah, not just you're doing it because like you're forced, somebody, you
know, has dragged you out. But you're going to do a מצווה
*mitzvah*, then you have two thousand אמות Amot *amos* from wherever you
wind up. You get to the next city, you help this woman
give birth, then you have two thousand אמות Amot *amos* from your
new place.
And even if you didn't do an עירוב *eiruv* before.
Yeah, yeah, right, even though you went outside of the תחום Techum
*techum*. Now, so the משנה *mishna* something fascinating, the משנה *mishna* assumes
you know that, that when you go out ברשות *birshus* you have
two thousand אמות Amot? *amos*, but but now it deals with the
following scenario. מי שיצא ברשות *Mi she-yatza birshus* you went out ברשות
*birshus* ואמרו לו כבר נעשה מעשה *ve'amru lo k'var na'asa ma'aseh*. And
they said, they said, oh, your services are no longer needed, we
found another midwife, she already gave birth, let's use that example. Okay.
So there you are, and it wound up that, you know, you
don't need to continue going, you're no longer involved in a מצווה
*mitzvah*, and so how much are you stuck? So יש לו אלפיים
אמה לכל רוח *yesh lo al-payim ama le-chol ruach*. So therefore, wherever
you found out that you're no longer needed, you have two thousand
אמות Amot. *amos*. You don't get to go to the city and
have two thousand אמות Amot *amos* from the city. So you still
might be a little stuck. Okay, this might be a bad policy
decision.
הצלה *Hatzolah* deals with this all the time. I'm sure. What would
you say? הצלה *Hatzolah*, they go somewhere ברשות *birshus* and then the
question is...
Right, now that's also the question about about התירו סופן משום תחלתן
*hitiru sofan mishum techilatan* and letting people go back or they wouldn't
go, and it's doctors and we'll get to that, we'll get to
that at the end of the משנה *mishna*, but this is just
giving you two thousand אמות Amot *amos*, which is not such a
good policy because if you're you could be stuck in the middle
of the road with two thousand אמות Amot *amos*, you're not in
one city, you're not in the next city. So it's nice to
give you two thousand אמות Amot *amos*, but it's still a little
problem being stuck there. Okay. אם היה בתוך התחום כאילו לא יצא
ke'ilu lo yatza, *im haya b'soch hat'chum k'ilu lo yatza*. But if
you're still within the תחום Techum *techum*, it's like you didn't leave,
which is obvious, you didn't leave, you're in the תחום Techum *techum*.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will discuss what that means. כל היוצאין
להציל חוזרין למקומן *kol hayotzin le-hatzil chozrin limkomam*. And by the way,
when you actually went out you can go back. Now, now we
just said you couldn't. So maybe it means that you actually succeeded
in saving the in doing the... it's not like you were no
longer needed. Right, this last line does not seem exactly to connect,
because it seems like you can always go back and our משנה
*mishna* says you can't, but the difference could be that in our
משנה *mishna* it turned out that you weren't needed. Okay, but maybe
if you were needed you can go back. We'll see about that
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* first wants
to understand what this... so the last two parts of the משנה
*mishna* don't seem to make sense. So מאי *mai*, what does it
mean, אם היה בתוך התחום כאילו לא יצא *im haya b'soch hat'chum
k'ilu lo yatza*? If you were within the תחום Techum *techum* it's
like you didn't go out. Of course it's like you didn't go
out, you didn't go out. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, הכי קאמר *hachi
kama*, this is what it's saying. אם היה בתוך תחומו כאילו
לא יצא מתוך ביתו *im haya b'soch techumo k'ilu lo yatza m'toch
beiso*. If you're within your תחום Techum *techum*, it's like you did
not go outside of your house. Which means what? Which means that
let's say your, you know, your house is here, you went, you
went a thousand אמות Amot *amos*. Okay. And then they say you
have two thousand and then you found out. They say you have
two thousand in every direction. So do I have two thousand now?
I can go another two thousand in this direction? Or do I
go back to being in my house? So he says no, if
you're basically within the תחום Techum. *techum* of your house, you don't
get a new two thousand אמות Amot *amos*, you go back to
where you started שבת *Shabbos*. So גמרא *Gemara* says פשיטא *peshita*, obviously.
No, מהו דתימא *mahu de-teima*, I might have thought הואיל ואעקר אעקר
*ho'il ve-akar akar*, once you uprooted yourself, you uprooted yourself. So once
you sort of, you know, we regave you the two thousand אמות
Amot *amos* even though you never left your original two thousand אמות
Amot *amos* we gave you a new one, קא משמע לן *ka
mashma lan*, we don't say that. רחמי בר חייא *Rachumi bar Chiya*
אמר *amar* הכי קאמר *hachi kama*, this is what it means. אם
היו תחומים techumim שנתנו לו חכמים מובלעין בתוך תחומו כאילו לא יצא
מתחומו *im hayu t'chumim she-nosnu lo chachamim muvla'in b'soch techumo k'ilu lo
yatza mi-t'chumo*. So this is very this is a much more, you
know, or a bigger חידוש *chiddush*. Here's your here I guess here's
your house, okay. Here is no no. Here's where you are. I
guess yeah I don't know how to anyway here's where you're.
Okay.
Here's where you are. Your house was over here, I'm your house.
This is your two thousand אמות Amot *amos*. You find yourself out
here when you found out your services are not needed. From where
you are, your two thousand אמות Amot, *amos* back overlap your two
thousand אמות Amot. *amos* from your house. Okay. since your two thousand
אמות Amot from where you are overlap your original תחום, Techum you're
allowed to go all the way back to your house. We normally
wouldn't allow that because then you would always wind up having like
four thousand אמות or whatever, but in this case we see that
basically this is a special case where you have two places where
your תחום Techum. is defined. Your תחום techum. is defined where you
started שבת, that's your two thousand אמות, and you got a new
תחום of where you wound up, two thousand אמות. If those two
תחומין Techumin overlap, you're allowed to go back home. Okay. Now by
the way, I should say that רש"י Rashi says, in one place
רש"י Rashi has two reads of this גמרא, but in one read
according to this, not only are you allowed to go back home,
you really have two תחומין. Techumin. You are allowed to go from
your house two thousand אמות in that direction and from where you
are two thousand אמות in that direction and all the way back
to your house. Okay. You really get your new תחום and your
old תחום and they overlap and they become one big תחום of
almost eight thousand אמות. That's what רש"י Rashi says. Wait a minute,
let's take a look because we're running out of time, I just
want to read one example of the גמרא. Let's read it one
more minute.
במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What are they debating? מר סבר הבלעת תחומין
מילתא היא. Mar savar havlas techumin milsahi. One says if one gets
absorbed in the other, overlaps, it's significant, and therefore it gets you
back to your house or maybe even gives you both, it becomes
one big תחום. ומר סבר לאו מילתא היא. U'mar savar lav milsahi.
No, it would not do it, so once you left your two
thousand אמות, you really would be stuck and only the point is
just like you don't get a new one. Okay, so now the
גמרא says let's just read one example of this. אמר ליה אביי
לרבא, Amar leh Abaye l'Rava, so אביי Abaye said to רבא, ואת
לא תסבר דהבלעת תחומין מילתא היא? Ve'at lo tisbar d'havlas techumin milsahi?
You must agree to me that this actually makes sense. Why? ומה
אי שבת במערה, Uma iy shavat bim'ara, if you, if you basically
started שבת in a cave שבתוכה ארבעה אלפים ועל גגה פחות מארבעה
אלפים. shebetocho arba alafim ve'al gaga pachas me'arba alafim. If you look
at the picture in רש"י, Rashi, right? So at the bottom of
the cave it's four thousand, actually טפחים, Tefachim, four thousand, ארבעה אלפים,
arba alafim, it's four thousand אמות wide and at the top it's
less than four thousand אמות wide.
Four thousand אמות or you mean four, ארבע אמות?
No, I meant four thousand.
לא נמצא מהלכו כולו בחוץ לאלפים אמה? Lo nimtza mahalacho kulo bachutz
l'alpaim amot? Couldn't you go the whole thing and outside of two
thousand אמות? So what does that mean? I'll just draw you this
one case so we don't have to do it again tomorrow and
of course we don't have a thing. But okay, I'll try to
do it again with
three-dimensional, no, I'll do it like this, I'll do it three-dimensional. Okay.
Here's your cave. You can go in down into the cave on
this side, great,
you can go down into the cave, right, on this side or
on this side. Okay. On the bottom is four thousand אמות. Now
if you started, let's say you're down here, you go out of
the cave and you come out on this side. Okay. So you're
given two thousand אמות in this direction. Okay. If you were to
come out on this side, you'd be given two thousand אמות in
that direction. Okay. Now so therefore, but practically, right, you can, if
you want, if you started here, right, you could, you would be
able to, if you start on the bottom of the cave, you'd
be able to go two thousand אמות this direction, two thousand אמות
this direction, the whole length here, all right, even though in the
end you're going more than four thousand אמות because ultimately you're at
the bottom of the cave and that overlaps to each. If you
started at the openings, right, if you started here, if you literally
started שבת here, you'd only have two thousand אמות this way. If
you started שבת here, you'd have two thousand אמות anyway.
What? I mean...
but this way you get because you started at the bottom of
the cave and the bottom of the cave is all surrounded by
walls, it's all one space, right, essentially, it's all one space. So
therefore it gives you, all of this is considered one space and
it gives you two thousand אמות in each direction. But looked from
above ground, you have more than two thousand אמות because you've got
two thousand אמות, the entire top of the cave and another two
thousand אמות. So it sees this as that this, this תחום from
when you go here overlaps with this תחום. But because they're sort
of brought together because at the base of the cave it's all
one, right, because they're brought together, it allows you to have both
of the תחומין. Techumin. Now it's not a very good comparison at
all, which is why I wanted to get done with this today
and we'll just see the answer of the גמרא. The גמרא's answer
is אמר
ליה, so he said back to him, ולא שני לך בין היכא
דשבת ואית ליה מחיצות מבעוד יום להיכא דלא שבת ואית ליה מחיצות
מבעוד
יום? velo shani lecha bein heicha deshvas va'avei mechitzos mibod yom le'heicha
delo shvas va'avei mechitzos mibod yom? He says what's the... how do
you compare it? There, if you're at the bottom of the cave,
you're in a place surrounded by מחיצות. mechitzos. So of course the
fact that where you exit, okay, doesn't matter, you were in the
cave and you get two thousand אמות from wherever you're going to
exit the cave in either direction. But that's because it was all
one space. Here you're at your home and you left and just
because they overlap does not necessarily mean you're going to get both.
In the case of the cave it wasn't that the two openings
overlapped, it was that where you were at the bottom was surrounded
by מחיצות. mechitzos. both of the תחומים combined. Okay. So, the next
משנה. מי שהוציאוהו נכרים mi shehotziu'u nochrim או רוח רעה. o ruach
ra'ah. Someone who was taken out by gentiles or by a bad
spirit, meaning an insane spirit took him out of his תחום. אין
לו אלא ארבע אמות. ein lo ela arba amot. He has no
more than four cubits. Now, if חזרוהו, hechziruhu, if they returned him,
כאילו לא יצא, it's
as if he never left. נתנוהו בדיר או בסהר. netanuhu b'dir o
b'sahar. If they put him into a fold or into a corral,
רבן גמליאל ורבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומרים, Rabban Gamliel v'Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah omrim, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
say, מהלך את כולה,
mehalech et kullah, he can walk
the whole thing. רבי יהושע ורבי עקיבא אומרים, Rabbi Yehoshua v'Rabbi Akiva
omrim, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say, אין
לו אלא ארבע אמות, ein lo ela arba amot, he only has
four cubits. מעשה שבאו מפרנדיסין. ma'aseh sheba'u mi'Prundisin. There was a story
where they were coming from Brindisi, which was a port in Italy.
והפליגה ספינתם בים, v'hifligah sefinatam bayam, and their ship was sailing in
the sea. רבן גמליאל ורבי אלעזר בן עזריה הלכו את כולה. Rabban
Gamliel v'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah halchu et kullah. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
and רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah walked through the
whole ship. רבי יהושע ורבי עקיבא לא זזו מארבע אמות. Rabbi Yehoshua
v'Rabbi Akiva lo zazu m'arba amot. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva did not move more than four cubits, אלא שרצו
להחמיר על עצמם, ela sheratzu lehachmir al atzmam, because they wanted to
be strict with themselves.